const arr = [{"id":0,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following conditions is recombinant erythropoietin indicated for?","answers":[{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia due to thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia due to chronic kidney disease","bool":true},{"option":"Anemia due to malnutrition","bool":false}]},{"id":1,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A patient may present with hemolytic anemia because of genetic mutations in protein synthesis. What is the most common inherited disorder causing anemia in humans in this connection?","answers":[{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":true}]},{"id":2,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What is the advantage of fingerprinting?","answers":[{"option":"No special training required","bool":false},{"option":"It is applicable for all age groups","bool":false},{"option":"It is applicable for all people","bool":false},{"option":"It enables absolute identification of an individual","bool":true},{"option":"It does not require any special and expensive instruments","bool":false}]},{"id":3,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What is the single best test to confirm iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Plasma iron level","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"Total iron-binding capacity (TIBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin saturation","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma ferritin levels","bool":true}]},{"id":4,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 9-year-old boy is brought to the outpatient department after he developed prominent bruises on his extremities. There is a history of a recent viral infection. Labs show normal values of both prothrombin time (PT) and activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT). What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Bone marrow aplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-platelet antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"Von-Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false}]},{"id":5,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 30-year-old lady received 6 units of blood and developed carpopedal spasm and twitching in her hands, along with flushing of the face. What can be given to relieve her condition?","answers":[{"option":"Intravenous normal saline","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous water","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous calcium gluconate","bool":true},{"option":"Intravenous 5% dextrose","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous diazepam","bool":false}]},{"id":6,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 25-year-old female with a history of two miscarriages develops deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in her leg. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Antiphospholipid syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Behcet's syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Rheumatoid arthritis","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Overlap syndrome","bool":false}]},{"id":7,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following agents is a potent iron chelator?","answers":[{"option":"Succimer","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrous gluconate","bool":false},{"option":"Unithiol","bool":false},{"option":"Deferoxamine","bool":true},{"option":"Ferrous sulfate","bool":false}]},{"id":8,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 35-year-old man with a history of intravenous (IV) drug abuse has generalized lymphadenopathy. Which of the following tests would help in finding the cause of his lymphadenopathy?","answers":[{"option":"HIV serology","bool":true},{"option":"Histopathology","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasonography","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false}]},{"id":9,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Stunted and notched upper central incisors are most likely to be found in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Congenital syphilis","bool":true},{"option":"Scurvy","bool":false},{"option":"Rickets","bool":false},{"option":"Fetal alcohol syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Plummer vinson syndrome","bool":false}]},{"id":10,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A person with polycythemia vera will have which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Yellow and jaundiced","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Pink in colour","bool":false},{"option":"Well oxygenated","bool":false},{"option":"Cyanotic due to sluggish blood flow","bool":true}]},{"id":11,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 65-year-old male presents with a 2-month history of fever and weight loss. On examination, the spleen is palpable 6 cm below the left costal margin. Complete blood count (CBC) reveals leukocytes=125x10⁹/L, hemoglobin=7.0 gm/dL and platelets= 510X10³/µL . He is diagnosed with chronic myeloid leukemia. Which of the following defects is present in chronic myeloid leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"t(9:11)","bool":false},{"option":"t(9:22)","bool":true},{"option":"t(8:21)","bool":false},{"option":"t(11:21)","bool":false},{"option":"t(15:17)","bool":false}]},{"id":12,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"An eye witness claims the victims death occurred about 12 hours ago. Which of the finding will confirm the statement?","answers":[{"option":"Rigor mortis present all over","bool":true},{"option":"Lividity fully developed and fixed","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in chemical constituents of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)","bool":false},{"option":"Greenish patch over caecum","bool":false},{"option":"Rise in potassium content of vitreous humor","bool":false}]},{"id":13,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"How many subtypes is Hodgkin lymphoma is divided into?","answers":[{"option":"Four subtypes","bool":false},{"option":"Two subtypes","bool":false},{"option":"Three subtypes","bool":false},{"option":"Five subtypes","bool":true},{"option":"Ten subtypes","bool":false}]},{"id":14,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Putrefaction is said to be colliquative when there is which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Colour change at right iliac fossa","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue conversion into solid mass","bool":false},{"option":"Distention of abdominal cavity","bool":false},{"option":"Swollen, puffy, bloated face","bool":false},{"option":"Appearance of maggots","bool":true}]},{"id":15,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Conversion of plasminogen to plasmin is inhibited by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Alteplase","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Aminocaproic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false}]},{"id":16,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 2-year-old male child presented in emergency with sudden onset of jaundice and cola-colored urine since last night. He was put on antimalarial two days back for suspected malaria. On examination in addition to jaundice, he has anemia and splenomegaly without hepatomegaly or lymphadenopathy. His blood pressure is 80/50 mmHg, pulse rate 110/min, and no edema. What test will confirm \r\n a diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Liver function test","bool":false},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":false},{"option":"G6PD levels in red blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":false},{"option":"Urine D/R","bool":false}]},{"id":17,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following antibodies is cold-type hemolytic anemia due to?","answers":[{"option":"IgM antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"IgG antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"IgD antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"IgA antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"IgE antibodies","bool":false}]},{"id":18,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Maximum number of Reed-Sternberg cells are seen in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocyte predominant Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocyte depleted Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Burkitt Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Nodular sclerosis Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Mixed cellularity Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false}]},{"id":19,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"The levels of protein C and protein S depend on which vitamin?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin E","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin A","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin D","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false}]},{"id":20,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What number of teeth are in a eight-year-old child's mouth?","answers":[{"option":"24","bool":true},{"option":"20","bool":false},{"option":"16","bool":false},{"option":"30","bool":false},{"option":"12","bool":false}]},{"id":21,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Essentially all endemic forms of Burkitt lymphoma are associated with which pathogen?","answers":[{"option":"HCV","bool":false},{"option":"EBV","bool":true},{"option":"HTCL-I","bool":false},{"option":"HIV","bool":false},{"option":"HBV","bool":false}]},{"id":22,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"The process of decomposition in the air is twice as rapid as in water and eight times as rapid as in the soil this is called?","answers":[{"option":"Casper's dictum","bool":true},{"option":"Newton law","bool":false},{"option":"Locard's exchange principle","bool":false},{"option":"Siphon principle","bool":false},{"option":"Fudin's principle","bool":false}]},{"id":23,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Polycythemia vera is strongly associated with an activating point mutation in which of the following genes?","answers":[{"option":"Tyrosine kinase ABL","bool":false},{"option":"p53","bool":false},{"option":"Tyrosine kinase JAK2","bool":true},{"option":"Tyrosine kinase JAKI","bool":false},{"option":"Tyrosine kinase","bool":false}]},{"id":24,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A young female presents with a palpable cervical lymph node, and in her biopsy reveals Reed- Sternberg's cells. These cells are derived from which of the following cell types?","answers":[{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"T-lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"ß-lymphocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Eosinophil","bool":false}]},{"id":25,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Basophil leukocytosis is an indication for:","answers":[{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloproliferative disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic infection","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myelogenous leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Stenle inflammation","bool":false}]},{"id":26,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is responsible to facilitate absorption of oral iron preparations?","answers":[{"option":"Phosphoric acid","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of food in stomach","bool":false},{"option":"Antacids","bool":false},{"option":"Tetracyclines","bool":false},{"option":"Ascorbic acid","bool":true}]},{"id":27,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 6-year-old child, diagnosed with hereditary spherocytosis, complained of increased frequency of blood transfusions. Blood complete picture shows Hb=6.5 gm/dL, reticulocyte count=20%, TLC=4000/mm³, platelets=100,000/mm³. What will be the most appropriate treatment for this child?","answers":[{"option":"Corticosteroids with antithymhocytic globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":true},{"option":"Bone marrow transplant","bool":false},{"option":"Hydroxyurea","bool":false},{"option":"Repeated transfusions with iron chelation","bool":false}]},{"id":28,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A child is diagnosed with non-Hodgkin lymphoma. He has generalized lymphadenopathy. Chest X-ray shows a mediastinal mass and CT abdomen shows enlarged, multiple mesentric, and para aortic lymph nodes. What is the most likely stage of the disease?","answers":[{"option":"Stage III","bool":true},{"option":"Stage I","bool":false},{"option":"Stage IV","bool":false},{"option":"Stage V","bool":false},{"option":"Stage II","bool":false}]},{"id":29,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following groups of drugs is not used for the treatment of thrombosis?","answers":[{"option":"Antifibrinolytics","bool":true},{"option":"Anticoagulants","bool":false},{"option":"Antiplatelet drugs","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombin inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinolytics","bool":false}]},{"id":30,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Extravascular hemolysis occurs mainly in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"GIT","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph node","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":true},{"option":"Blood vessels","bool":false}]},{"id":31,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Hemoglobin (HbH) disease is caused by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Deletion of three alpha-globin genes","bool":true},{"option":"Deletion of beta-globin genes","bool":false},{"option":"Deletion of gamma-globin genes","bool":false},{"option":"Point mutation in a single alpha-globin gene","bool":false},{"option":"Deletion of delta-globin genes","bool":false}]},{"id":32,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Systemic viral infection, particularly in children often produce which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Acute lymphadenitis in inguinal region","bool":false},{"option":"Acute mesenteric adenitis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphadenitis in axillary region","bool":false},{"option":"Acute generalized lymphadenopathy","bool":true},{"option":"Acute lymphadenitis in cervical region","bool":false}]},{"id":33,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 4-year-old girl presents with skin pallor for the past 3 days. One week ago she had a history of bloody diarrhea. Examination showed petechiae on the upper limbs. Laboratory studies revealed Hb 7.1 g/dl, reticulocytes 14%, platelets 30x 109/L, and normal WBC count. The renal function is deranged. The peripheral smear features numerous schistocytes and occasional nucleated RBC. Given the findings, which of the following bacteria is involved in the pathophysiology of disease?","answers":[{"option":"Salmonella typhi","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus pyogenes","bool":false},{"option":"Staphylococcus aureus","bool":false},{"option":"Helicobacter pylori","bool":false},{"option":"Shigella dysenteriae","bool":true}]},{"id":34,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Stony hard lymph node is mostly suggestive of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberculosis","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Infection","bool":false},{"option":"Malignancy","bool":true}]},{"id":35,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 45-year-old man with acute myocardial infarction is given alteplase. Which statement best describes its effect?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibition of platelet thromboxane production","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibits synthesis of vitamin K-dependent coagulation factors","bool":false},{"option":"Prevents aggregation of adjacent platelets by blocking glycoprotein IIb/IIIa receptor","bool":false},{"option":"Blockade of ADP-platelet receptor","bool":false},{"option":"Rapidly activates plasmin","bool":true}]},{"id":36,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 2-year-old child comes to the hospital for circumcision. His two brothers also had bleeding diathesis. Which test should be done?","answers":[{"option":"D-dimers","bool":false},{"option":"Clotting time","bool":false},{"option":"aPTT","bool":true},{"option":"Bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"Urea clot lysis test","bool":false}]},{"id":37,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"ABO incompatibility occurs in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Post transfusion plupine","bool":false},{"option":"Transfusion of bacterial contaminated blood product","bool":false},{"option":"Febrile non-hemolytic transfusion reactions","bool":false},{"option":"Anaphylactic reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Acute hemolytic transfusion reactions","bool":true}]},{"id":38,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Spontaneous bleeding becomes evident when the platelet count falls below which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"40,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"60,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"100,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"75,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"20,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":true}]},{"id":39,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 45-year-old male who is bed-bound from paraplegia develops sudden shortness of breath. On examination, his right calf is found to be swollen and tender, a provisional diagnosis of deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism is made. What will be the single most sought diagnostic test?","answers":[{"option":"Doppler venous ultrasonography","bool":false},{"option":"Echocardiography","bool":false},{"option":"Electrocardiography (ECG)","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography (CT) pulmonary angiography","bool":true},{"option":"X-ray chest","bool":false}]},{"id":40,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 30-year-old female admitted with anemic failure for which she received six units of stored whole blood. After 24 hours she develops twitching on the face and carpopedal spasm of hands. What is the best treatment option?","answers":[{"option":"Give her I/V slowly calcium gluconate infusion","bool":true},{"option":"Give her I/V diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Give her I/V magnesium sulphate","bool":false},{"option":"Give her I/V 5% dextrose water","bool":false},{"option":"Give her I/V normal saline","bool":false}]},{"id":41,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 25-year-old female presents with sudden onset pain in the right upper limb on examination right upper limb is pale, cold, extremely tender with absent radial and brachial pulses on the right side. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Myositis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute limb ischemia","bool":true},{"option":"Venous thrombosis","bool":false},{"option":"Osteomyelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Humerus fracture","bool":false}]},{"id":42,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What is the most appropriate treatment for a 5-year-old child with hereditary spherocytosis, large spleen, with hemoglobin mostly remaining at 7-9gm/dl, and reticulocyte count at 12-15%?","answers":[{"option":"Hydroxyurea","bool":false},{"option":"Regular blood transfusions with deferral","bool":true},{"option":"Regular blood transfusions","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow transplant","bool":false},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":false}]},{"id":43,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"For a functional platelet disorder, which of the following is a correct statement?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombocytopenia, PT and APTT will be normal","bool":false},{"option":"Normal platelet count, PT & APTT will be prolonged","bool":false},{"option":"Normal platelet count, APTT will be prolonged","bool":false},{"option":"Normal or low platelet count, PT & APTT will be normal","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia, only PT will be prolonged","bool":false}]},{"id":44,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which investigation(s) is/are the first step investigating a case of thrombosis?","answers":[{"option":"Antiphospholipid antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Lupus anticoagulant","bool":false},{"option":"D-dimers","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin time","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V Leiden","bool":false}]},{"id":45,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A guy who shoots himself tends to get instantaneous rigor instead of rigor mortis. Which one of the following statements most likely signifies the difference between the two?","answers":[{"option":"Muscle contraction is less marked in instantaneous rigor mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Primary relaxation is absent in instantaneous rigor mortis","bool":true},{"option":"Instantaneous rigor indicates time of death instead of mode of death","bool":false},{"option":"Instantaneous rigor affects all the muscles","bool":false},{"option":"Instantaneous rigor mortis is not immediate after the death","bool":false}]},{"id":46,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following foods has the best iron absorption from the intestines?","answers":[{"option":"Pomegranate","bool":false},{"option":"Pulses","bool":false},{"option":"Red meat","bool":true},{"option":"Oranges","bool":false},{"option":"Mangoes","bool":false}]},{"id":47,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What is the most common condition leading to disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) in hospitalized patients?","answers":[{"option":"Severe infection","bool":true},{"option":"Snake bite","bool":false},{"option":"Malignancy","bool":false},{"option":"Trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Vascular aneurysms","bool":false}]},{"id":48,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which iron preparation can be given only by the intravenous route?","answers":[{"option":"Sodium ferrous gluconate complex","bool":false},{"option":"Iron fructose complex","bool":false},{"option":"Sodium ferric gluconate complex","bool":true},{"option":"Ferrous gluconate dessicated","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrous fumarate","bool":false}]},{"id":49,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is correct regarding nutritional anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Most common cause is folate deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"It is a disease syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Does not present with signs and symptms","bool":false},{"option":"Most common cause is iron deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Cannot be recovered","bool":false}]},{"id":50,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What is the most common chromosomal change in acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)?","answers":[{"option":"t(14; 18)","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperploidy","bool":true},{"option":"t(11; 18)","bool":false},{"option":"Trisomy 12","bool":false},{"option":"t(8; 14)","bool":false}]},{"id":51,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following inherited bleeding disorders almost always occurs in males?","answers":[{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":true},{"option":"Factor XIII deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V deficiency","bool":false}]},{"id":52,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 25-year-old male presents to the clinic with easy fatigability and generalized weakness. On examination he has blood pressure (BP)=110/60 mm of Hg, looks pale, and has koilonychia. His complete blood count (CBC) shows: Hb=9.7 g/dl, MCV=69 fl, MCHC=26 g/dl. What is the most likely cause of anemia in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia minor","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Thalassemia major","bool":false},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":53,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following triggers the extrinsic clotting mechanism?","answers":[{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Thromboplastin","bool":true},{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"White blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Adenosine","bool":false}]},{"id":54,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Corticosteroid-induced immunosuppression involves which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Modification of T cell mediated response","bool":false},{"option":"B-lymphocyte activation inhibition","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased production of interleukins","bool":false},{"option":"All of these","bool":true},{"option":"Mast cell stabilization","bool":false}]},{"id":55,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 64-year-old male presents to the hospital with excruciating back pain, His erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) and creatinine levels are markedly raised. The clinical diagnosis made by the physician is multiple myeloma. What will be the most characteristic findings on his serum protein electrophoresis?","answers":[{"option":"Polyclonal broad band in gamma region","bool":false},{"option":"Single sharp discrete band in gamma region","bool":true},{"option":"Single sharp band in alpha region","bool":false},{"option":"Single sharp band in beta 2 region","bool":false},{"option":"Single sharp band in albumin region","bool":false}]},{"id":56,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"The subdivision of lymphomas into Hodgkin's and Non-Hodgkin's lymphomas is based on the\r\nhistological presence of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Reed–Sternberg cells","bool":true},{"option":"Kupffer cells","bool":false},{"option":"Natural killer cells (NK-cells)","bool":false},{"option":"T-cells","bool":false}]},{"id":57,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"In myeloproliferative disorders, there is a proliferation of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Myeloid progenitors","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false}]},{"id":58,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 45-year-old male presents with a 2-month history of fever and weight loss. On examination, massive splenomegaly is observed. Complete blood count (CBC) reveals leukocyte count=165x10⁹/L, hemoglobin= 9.0 gm/dL and platelets=510 X10³/µL . He is diagnosed with chronic myeloid leukemia. Which of the following molecular defects is present in chronic myeloid leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"c-Myc gene fusion","bool":false},{"option":"BCL6 gene fusion","bool":false},{"option":"BCR-ABL gene fusion","bool":true},{"option":"RAR alpha (RARA) gene fusion","bool":false},{"option":"p53 gene mutation","bool":false}]},{"id":59,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"An 8-year-old child is brought to the hospital with complaints of fever for 2 months along with hepatomegaly and splenomegaly. Investigations show the following: Hb=4.8 gm/dl, TLC=1700/HPF, platelets=38000. Peripheral smear shows microcytic anemia with blast cells. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sepsis/disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)","bool":false},{"option":"Typhoid fever","bool":false},{"option":"Malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Acute leukemia","bool":true}]},{"id":60,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"For the purpose of determining age and sex from the skeleton of an unknown dead body, maximum information can be obtained by examining which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Metacarpals","bool":false},{"option":"Ribs","bool":false},{"option":"Vertebrae","bool":false},{"option":"Radius and ulna","bool":false},{"option":"Skull and mandible","bool":true}]},{"id":61,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A fresh victim of a road traffic accident is brought to the emergency department but lost his life on the\r\nway to the hospital. To confirm his death, the body is examined for all immediate signs of death. Which of\r\nthe following is an immediate sign of death?","answers":[{"option":"Secondary relaxation","bool":false},{"option":"Rigor Mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Primary relaxation","bool":true},{"option":"Algor mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Postmortem lividity","bool":false}]},{"id":62,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 22-year-old woman attends an antenatal booking appointment. She has had previous 3 miscarriages. She has mouth ulcers and joint pains and is evaluated for arthritis/ arthralgia. Which single pair of results are most likely to confirm the underlying cause of her symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Increased erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) and rheumatoid factor","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease hemoglobin and increased reticulocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased hemoglobin and decreased mean corpuscular volume (MCV)","bool":false},{"option":"Increased lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) and increased bilirubin","bool":false},{"option":"Increased activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) and decreased platelets","bool":true}]},{"id":63,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"The dead body of a young female is recovered from her house hanging from a fan. On examination it is seen that post mortem lividity in lower limbs is fully developed and fixed. If, in the dead body, the post mortem lividity does not blanch on applying pressure, what will be the probable time elapsed since her death?","answers":[{"option":"6-8 hours","bool":true},{"option":"10-12 hours","bool":false},{"option":"3-6 hours","bool":false},{"option":"0-3 hours","bool":false},{"option":"1-3 hours","bool":false}]},{"id":64,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Tests for coagulation profile usually include; bleeding time, clotting time, prothrombin time (PT) and\r\nactivated partial prothrombin time (aPTT). Prolonged bleeding time with normal PT and APTT is indicative\r\nof which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Von-Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":true},{"option":"Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Vascular disorders","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false}]},{"id":65,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"The process of margination of neutrophils is mediated by the reaction between which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Integrin and interleukin-7 (IL-7)","bool":false},{"option":"Gamma interferon and integrin","bool":false},{"option":"Intracellular adhesion molecule-I and chemokines","bool":false},{"option":"Selectins and integrins","bool":true},{"option":"Integrin and major basic protein","bool":false}]},{"id":66,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 72-year-old man is brought to the emergency department with sudden onset of acute arterial occlusions of the right lower limb leading to gangrene of the lower leg and foot. He has lens subluxation and a long tapering finger. What is the most probable cause of this acute arterial occlusion?","answers":[{"option":"Homocysteinemia","bool":true},{"option":"Protein C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V leiden mutant gene","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia vera","bool":false},{"option":"Antiphospholipid antibody syndrome","bool":false}]},{"id":67,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What is the replacement source in the therapy of hemophilia A?","answers":[{"option":"Recombinant factor VIII products","bool":true},{"option":"Recombinant factor VII A","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombrin complex concentrates","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false}]},{"id":68,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 10-year-old child with a known case of thalassemia major requires red cell transfusion every month, since the age of one year. For the last 5 to 6 months, he develops urticarial rashes during transfusion. What\r\nwill be an appropriate step for management?","answers":[{"option":"Prior to transfusion, give him one shot of steroid","bool":false},{"option":"Transfuse whole blood","bool":false},{"option":"Transfuse washed red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Transfuse Rh-negative blood","bool":false},{"option":"Prior to transfusion, give him antihistamine and antipyretic drugs","bool":true}]},{"id":69,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What is the cephalic index?","answers":[{"option":"The ratio of the maximum breadth of the skull and anterioposterior length of skull","bool":true},{"option":"Sum of the maximum breadth of the skull and the maximum length of skull","bool":false},{"option":"Maximum anteroposterior length of skull","bool":false},{"option":"The maximum transverse breadth of skull","bool":false},{"option":"Superimposition technique","bool":false}]},{"id":70,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A decapitated dead body of a male is brought for autopsy. What will be the most important part of an autopsy in this case for further identification?","answers":[{"option":"Taking photographs","bool":false},{"option":"Preservation of 1st vertebra of the body distal to the cut","bool":false},{"option":"Taking bone marrow for DNA fingerprinting","bool":false},{"option":"Taking fingerprints of the body","bool":true},{"option":"Taking poor prints","bool":false}]},{"id":71,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following best suits the definition of hemolysis?","answers":[{"option":"Premature destruction of red blood cells (RBCs)","bool":true},{"option":"Loss of blood via bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Peripheral destruction of platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Extravasation of blood in skin","bool":false},{"option":"Under production of red blood cells","bool":false}]},{"id":72,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What is the prime objective in bone marrow transplantation?","answers":[{"option":"Get rid of the primary disease","bool":true},{"option":"Make patient pancytopenic","bool":false},{"option":"To inhibit graft versus host disease (GVHD)","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotherapy to kill the malignant disease","bool":false},{"option":"To initiate graft versus host disease (GVHD)","bool":false}]},{"id":73,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"The indication for hematopoietic stem cell transplants does not include the following?","answers":[{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Hematologic malignancies","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Non-hematologic cancers","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false}]},{"id":74,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A boy is convicted of a criminal offense and the judge of the juvenile court orders to send him to a reformatory school. This is because his age is less than which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"15 years","bool":false},{"option":"14 years","bool":false},{"option":"16 years","bool":false},{"option":"18 years","bool":true},{"option":"17 years","bool":false}]},{"id":75,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A male aged about 16-17 years is sent to confirm his age. Advisable single radiograph would be which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Sternum","bool":false},{"option":"Skull","bool":false},{"option":"Wrist joint","bool":false},{"option":"Elbow joint","bool":true}]},{"id":76,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 70-year-old male presents to the hospital with severe backache. His investigations reveal Hb=7 gm/dl, creatinine=2 mg/dL, ESR= 110 mm/hour. What other finding is most likely to be found on investigations?","answers":[{"option":"Hypernatremia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypocalcemia","bool":false},{"option":"Raised serum alkaline phosphatase","bool":false},{"option":"Hypercalcemia","bool":true},{"option":"Bone scan showing increased uptake","bool":false}]},{"id":77,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 10-year-old child who is otherwise healthy got a complete blood count done which showed Hb of 10 gm/dL, with hypochromic and microcytic red cell indices. Her pediatrician is assuming her to be a carrier of the beta-thalassemia trait. Which of the following tests will confirm her diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":false},{"option":"Blood culture","bool":false},{"option":"Schilling test","bool":false}]},{"id":78,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"According to the expanded program of immunization (EPI), the second dose of the measles vaccine is recommended to be given at what age?","answers":[{"option":"1 year","bool":false},{"option":"15 months","bool":true},{"option":"6 months","bool":false},{"option":"18 month","bool":false},{"option":"9 months","bool":false}]},{"id":79,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What is the best long term treatment in a patient with cerebrovascular accident (CVA) after arterial thrombosis with anti-phospholipid syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Physiotherapy","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":true},{"option":"Lipid-lowering medicine","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false}]},{"id":80,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"During the exhumation of an unidentified grave, a human skeleton was recovered.  What will be the most reliable bones to determine sex?","answers":[{"option":"Skull","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Skull and pelvis","bool":true},{"option":"Femur","bool":false},{"option":"Skull and femur","bool":false}]},{"id":81,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is least likely to be a clinical feature of aplastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Blood blisters in the mouth","bool":false},{"option":"Bleeding gums and epistaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Ecchymoses","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphadenopathy and hepatosplenomegaly","bool":true},{"option":"Bleeding with minimal trauma","bool":false}]},{"id":82,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Why is parenteral administration of folic acid not favored in patients?","answers":[{"option":"Given orally because it is very tasty and hence the patient's compliance is very high","bool":false},{"option":"Its profound deficiency is not seen in human beings","bool":false},{"option":"It is well absorbed orally even in patients with malabsorption syndromes","bool":true},{"option":"It is rapidly metabolized and eliminated","bool":false},{"option":"It is too painful through the parenteral route","bool":false}]},{"id":83,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Different blood products are transfused in different clinical conditions. Which product is required if\r\na patient is bleeding actively and has deficiencies of multiple coagulation factors?","answers":[{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":true},{"option":"Cryoprecipitate","bool":false},{"option":"Whole blood","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet","bool":false},{"option":"Packed red blood cells","bool":false}]},{"id":84,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 22-year-old African American man went to the hospital to determine if he has sickle cell trait. Which one of the following laboratory tests can be used to detect the presence of hemoglobin S?","answers":[{"option":"Schillings test","bool":false},{"option":"Metabisulfite test","bool":true},{"option":"Coombs test","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose tolerance test","bool":false},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":false}]},{"id":85,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following antibodies are present in Bernard-Soulier syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Glycoprotein IIa","bool":false},{"option":"Glycoprotein Ib antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"Glycoprotein IIa/IIIb antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Glycoprotein Ib/IIIb antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet membrane phospholipids","bool":false}]},{"id":86,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"In hemophilia, there is a prolongation of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"PT, aPTT, and bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"Bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"aPTT","bool":true},{"option":"PT and aPTT","bool":false},{"option":"PT","bool":false}]},{"id":87,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"An 11-year-old child is diagnosed with acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Which of the following is the most important factor in classifying leukemia as a high-risk group?","answers":[{"option":"Platelet count less than 50,000","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocyte count less than 1500","bool":false},{"option":"Age of the child between 1-10 years","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocyte count greater than 50,000","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobin less than 5 gm/dl","bool":false}]},{"id":88,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is correct regarding the mixed cellularity variant of Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Immunophenotype is not classical","bool":false},{"option":"The mononuclear variant of Reed-Sternberg cells is seen","bool":true},{"option":"Not associated with Epstein–Barr virus (EBV)","bool":false},{"option":"It is seen in 5% of cases","bool":false},{"option":"Monotonous cellular infiltrate is the hallmark","bool":false}]},{"id":89,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) is found in 30-40% of cases of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Burkitt's lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Kaposi's sarcoma","bool":false}]},{"id":90,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Immune cell antigen CD4 is associated with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Natural killer cells","bool":false},{"option":"Mature T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Thymocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Helper T-cells","bool":true},{"option":"Cytotoxic T-cells","bool":false}]},{"id":91,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is not a presentation of a patient with a disorder of primary hemostasis?","answers":[{"option":"Petechia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Menorrhagia","bool":false},{"option":"Ecchymosis","bool":false},{"option":"Gum bleeding","bool":false}]},{"id":92,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A cord blood sample of an Rh-ve mother was sent for laboratory testing during labor. Which of the following would indicate the need for blood exchange transfusion?","answers":[{"option":"Peripheral cells shows spherocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte is corrected to 7%","bool":true},{"option":"Indirect coombs test is weakly negative","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin = 10 mg/dL","bool":false},{"option":"Serum bilirubin = 2.5 mg/dL","bool":false}]},{"id":93,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A patient has presented with iron deficiency anemia and was prescribed treatment with iron supplements. Which single test would show early response to the treatment?","answers":[{"option":"Total Iron Binding capacity","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte count","bool":true},{"option":"Blood Complete picture","bool":false},{"option":"Iron","bool":false}]},{"id":94,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which one of the following statements is correct regarding vitamin B12 and folic acid?","answers":[{"option":"Deficiency of either vitamin B12 or folic acid impairs DNA synthesis","bool":true},{"option":"Pernicious anemia should be treated with folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of folic acid is usually associated with neurological abnormalities","bool":false},{"option":"Lack of plasma transferrin causes the malabsorption of vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"To treat patient with a deficiency of intrinsic factor, vitamin B12 should be administered orally","bool":false}]},{"id":95,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"In chronic myeloid leukemia, there is a predominant proliferation of which cells?","answers":[{"option":"Eosinophil precursors","bool":false},{"option":"Erythroid precursors","bool":false},{"option":"Basophil precursors","bool":true},{"option":"Granulocyte precursors","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophil and myeloid precursors","bool":false}]},{"id":96,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Virchowis Node is pathological enlargement of:","answers":[{"option":"Right jugulodigastric lymph node","bool":false},{"option":"Left jugulodigastric lymph node","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior Cervical Chain Lymph Node","bool":false},{"option":"Right Supra-Clavicular Lymph Node","bool":false},{"option":"Left Supra-Clavicular Lymph Node","bool":true}]},{"id":97,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura can be successfully treated by which of the following methods?","answers":[{"option":"Dialysis which remove auto antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Catheterization which remove plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous infusion which removes the antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet infusion which removes basal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma exchange which remove auto antibodies","bool":true}]},{"id":98,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Why does sickling occur in sickle cell anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Polycythaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Increase red cell counts","bool":false},{"option":"Low oxygen tension in tissues","bool":true},{"option":"Increased haemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"RBC shape","bool":false}]},{"id":99,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"In graft versus host (GVHD) disease, which organ is most commonly affected?","answers":[{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Skin","bool":false},{"option":"GIT","bool":true},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Heart","bool":false}]},{"id":100,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 50-year-old male was diagnosed with a case of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. His hemoglobin was 6 gm/dL. Peripheral smear shows anemia. Which type of anemia are non-Hodgkin lymphomas mostly associated with?","answers":[{"option":"Anemia due to bone marrow infiltration","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":true},{"option":"Dry induced anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":101,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Best indicator of air pollution is/are:","answers":[{"option":"Smoke, suspended particles and SO2","bool":false},{"option":"Carbon monoxide","bool":false},{"option":"Sulphur dioxide","bool":false},{"option":"Particulate matter","bool":true},{"option":"Methane","bool":false}]},{"id":102,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 21-year-old female has a history of recurrent blood transfusion. On examination she is anemic and her spleen is enlarged 6 cm below the left costal margin. Hb=7.3 g/dL, MCV=50 fL, reticulocyte count=3.5%. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Pyruvate kinase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":true}]},{"id":103,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following foods have best iron absorption from the intestine?","answers":[{"option":"Mangoes","bool":false},{"option":"Pulses","bool":false},{"option":"Pomogrenate","bool":false},{"option":"Oranges","bool":false},{"option":"Red meat","bool":true}]},{"id":104,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is the result of vitamin B12 deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Impaired collagen formation","bool":false},{"option":"Impaired coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"Impaired hemoglobin synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Hematopoietic stem cell failure","bool":false},{"option":"Impaired DNA synthesis","bool":true}]},{"id":105,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 1-year-old child is recently diagnosed with beta-thalassemia major. Which of the following will be the most characteristic findings on a peripheral film of the child?","answers":[{"option":"Poikilocytosis, hypochromia, microcytosis, target cells, and fragmented red blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"Hyporchromia, microcytosis, and sickled cells","bool":false},{"option":"Bite cells, blister cells, and spherocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Microspherocytes, polychromasia, and nucleated red blood vells","bool":false},{"option":"Macro-ovalocytes with nuclear hypersegmentation","bool":false}]},{"id":106,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What is the primary mechanism by which heparin prevents coagulation of blood?","answers":[{"option":"Direct inhibition of the conversion of prothrombin to thrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of calcium","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of factors XIIa and XIIIa","bool":false},{"option":"Facilitation of antithrombin III mediated inhibition of factor Xa and thrombin","bool":true},{"option":"Activation of antithrombin III to inhibit factors IX and XI","bool":false}]},{"id":107,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 5-year-old child with a known case of eczema also develops rhinitis and gets asthmatic with seasonal change. She is brought to the outpatient department and a complete blood count is advised. Which cell would be in high number is this case?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinphils","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false}]},{"id":108,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A dead body is brought to the mortuary for post mortem examination, having post mortem rigidity present in the whole body from head to toe. What is the estimated time since the death?","answers":[{"option":"24-36 hours","bool":false},{"option":"36-48 hours","bool":false},{"option":"4-18 hours","bool":false},{"option":"12-24 hours","bool":true},{"option":"2-4 hours","bool":false}]},{"id":109,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"What are the differentiating features of the female pelvis?","answers":[{"option":"Obturator foramen is large","bool":false},{"option":"Sub-pubic angle V-shaped","bool":false},{"option":"Ischial tuberosity is inverted","bool":false},{"option":"Pre-auricular sulcus less prominent","bool":false},{"option":"Sub-pubic angle U-shaped, and obtuse","bool":true}]},{"id":110,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 29-year-old female comes for a routine checkup as part of a pre-employment requirement. Her complete blood count reveals Hb= 10 gm/dL with microcytic hypochromic red cell indices. Assuming that she is a carrier of the beta-thalassemia trait, what will be the most likely findings on her hemoglobin electrophoresis to confirm her carrier status?","answers":[{"option":"Normal HbA and increased Hb A2 (3-5%)","bool":false},{"option":"Normal HbA and A2, but slightly increased HbF","bool":false},{"option":"Normal HbA and A2, but markedly increased HbF (>90%)","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased HbA,and raised HbA2 and HbF","bool":true},{"option":"Normal HbA and increased Hb A2 (4-8%)","bool":false}]},{"id":111,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 40-year-old male bed-bound from paraplegia is diagnosed with deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in his right leg. He develops a sudden onset of shortness of breath. A subsequent diagnosis of pulmonary embolism is made. What will be the most common initial electrocardiography (ECG) finding?","answers":[{"option":"S1Q3T3 pattern","bool":false},{"option":"ST segment elevation","bool":false},{"option":"Right bundle branch block","bool":false},{"option":"Sinus tachycardia","bool":true},{"option":"Non-specific T wave inversion","bool":false}]},{"id":112,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 20-year-old male is brought to the outpatient department with a history of painless cervical lymphadenopathy and a physician is suspecting malignancy. What is the key investigation required to get a diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Fine needle aspiration (FNA)","bool":false},{"option":"Excisional biopsy of the node","bool":true},{"option":"Chest X-ray (CXR)","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR)","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false}]},{"id":113,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 20-year-old male presents to the outpatient department with a history of fever and night sweats for the past two months. On examination, multiple cervical lymph nodes are palpable which are painless and matted. Which of the following is the single best diagnostic option?","answers":[{"option":"Mantoux test","bool":false},{"option":"High levels of erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR)","bool":false},{"option":"Fine needle aspiration cytology (FNAC)","bool":false},{"option":"Excisional biopsy of the node","bool":true},{"option":"Supportive evidence by chest X-ray (CXR)","bool":false}]},{"id":114,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is the correct sequence of steps in bone marrow transplantation?","answers":[{"option":"Collection, chemotherapy, infusion","bool":false},{"option":"Collection, processing, cryopreservation, infusion","bool":false},{"option":"Collection, cryopreservation, chemotherapy, infusion","bool":false},{"option":"Collection, processing, cryopreservation, chemotherapy, infusion","bool":true},{"option":"Collection, infusion","bool":false}]},{"id":115,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A detective is searching for evidence at a crime scene when he encounters fingerprints on the doorknob. He takes the impressions for examination. Inspection reveals that the pattern resembles hairpin heads that are elongated in the left direction. What is the most likely fingerprint pattern in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Loop","bool":true},{"option":"Composite","bool":false},{"option":"Arch","bool":false},{"option":"Whorl","bool":false},{"option":"Tented arch","bool":false}]},{"id":116,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Primary immune thrombocytopenia occurs due to which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Systemic lupus erythmatosus (SLE)","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Auto-antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false}]},{"id":117,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A young boy is arrested due to a criminal charge. The court orders for a detailed forensic examination to determine his age. Pelvic X-ray findings show that the ischium and pubis are not united. What is the approximate age of the boy?","answers":[{"option":"Less than 18 years","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 7 years","bool":true},{"option":"25 years or more","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 12 years","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 25 years","bool":false}]},{"id":118,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 21-year-old female presents with petechiae on her skin and episodes of epistaxis for the last two months. On examination, there is no hepatosplenomegaly or lymphadenopathy. Which of the following is the most sensitive earliest test for making a diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Antinuclear antibody (ANA) profile","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte count","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet count","bool":true},{"option":"Liver function test","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow aspiration","bool":false}]},{"id":119,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 35-year-old male known case of chronic myeloid leukemia shows massive splenomegaly on clinical examination. Complete blood count (CBC) reveals WBC count=165x10^9/L, Hb= 9.0 gm/dL and platelets=510 X10^3. Which of the following targeted therapy is specific for chronic myeloid leukemia patients?","answers":[{"option":"Jak-2 inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-CD20 antibody","bool":false},{"option":"Check point inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Tyrosine kinase inhibitors","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombopoietin receptor agonists","bool":false}]},{"id":120,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 60-year-old patient presented with anorexia, weakness, paraesthesia, and mental changes. His tongue was red, tendon reflexes were diminished, and hemoglobin was 6 gm/dL with large red cells and hypersegmented neutrophils. Endoscopy revealed atrophic gastritis. Deficiency of which factor is likely to be responsible for his condition?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin E","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":true},{"option":"Riboflavin","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Pyridoxine","bool":false}]},{"id":121,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"The age of a young boy needs to be determined. Dental X-ray reveals mixed dentition and examination of the oral cavity reveals that the first molars have erupted. What is the approximate age of this boy?","answers":[{"option":"5-7 years","bool":false},{"option":"16-18 years","bool":false},{"option":"10-12 years","bool":false},{"option":"6-9 years","bool":false},{"option":"6-7 years","bool":true}]},{"id":122,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"The approximate age of a girl needs to be determined as ordered by the court. After getting a series of X-rays done, it is revealed that she has only 3 carpal bones ossified. What is the likely age of the girl?","answers":[{"option":"10","bool":false},{"option":"1","bool":false},{"option":"6","bool":false},{"option":"7","bool":false},{"option":"3","bool":true}]},{"id":123,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 2-year-old boy presents with a history of anemia. His spleen is just palpable. Lab findings reveal Hb=10 gm/dL, MCV=67 fL, high HbA2 (7%), normal HbF, and a normal iron profile. Which of the following best corresponds to this clinical picture?","answers":[{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia minor","bool":true},{"option":"Alpha-thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia major","bool":false}]},{"id":124,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A person undergoes ileal resection. After some days he develops weakness, shortness of breath, and anemia. Which anemia can it possibly be?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic blood loss anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":125,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which interleukin is required for the growth and proliferation of all the stem cells?","answers":[{"option":"Interleukin-2","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-3","bool":true},{"option":"Interleukin-1","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-5","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-4","bool":false}]},{"id":126,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 25-year-old pregnant woman is found to have microcytic anemia during her antenatal visits. Her Hb is 7 mg/dL with an MCV of 66 fL. Which of the following is the single best test for the confirmation of iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Serum ferritin levels","bool":true},{"option":"Transferrin saturation","bool":false},{"option":"Total iron binding capacity (TIBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Serum iron levels","bool":false},{"option":"Hb electrophoresis","bool":false}]},{"id":127,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 30-year-old man presents with a history of hematuria for 15 days. He also had an episode of gum bleed one day back. Considering idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP) as the diagnosis, which of the following is the best initial treatment of choice?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombopoietin agonist","bool":false},{"option":"Danazole","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmapheresis","bool":false},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":false},{"option":"Corticosteroids","bool":true}]},{"id":128,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 57-year-old man presents with hypertrophy of gums and is diagnosed with acute myeloid leukemia (AML). Which of the following is characteristic of this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Auer rods","bool":true},{"option":"Ringed sideroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Reed-Sternberg cells","bool":false},{"option":"Burr cells","bool":false},{"option":"Howell Jolly bodies","bool":false}]},{"id":129,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 34-year-old woman presents to the clinic with pallor, jaundice, and splenomegaly. Her complete blood count shows Hb 9 g/dL and MCV 107 fL. Direct Coomb's test is positive. She is diagnosed with warm autoimmune hemolytic anemia and treated with steroids, but the patient does not respond. Which of the following is the next best step in management?","answers":[{"option":"Transfusion","bool":false},{"option":"Azathioprine","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclophosphamide","bool":false},{"option":"Rituximab","bool":true},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":false}]},{"id":130,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 60-year-old woman presents with a 4-month history of progressive lethargy and recurrent throat infections. Recently, she developed gum bleeding and noticed purpura all over her body. She is anemic, but the remainder of the examination is normal. Investigations show Hb 7 g/dL, white cell count 83000/uL, and platelets 18000/uL. Bone marrow biopsy shows hypercellular marrow with a decrease in normal precursor cells.; 85% of the cells are myeloblasts. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":131,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 50-year-old man presents to the clinic with marked heaviness in the left hypochondrium. He has also had experienced early satiety for 3 months. On examination, the liver is enlarged, 3 cm below the costal margin amd the spleen is massively enlarged up to the umbilicus. Considering myelofibrosis as a diagnosis, which of the following is the only approved treatment?","answers":[{"option":"Immunotherapy","bool":false},{"option":"Interferon","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow transplantation","bool":false},{"option":"Ruxolitinib","bool":true},{"option":"Platelet aggregation inhibitor","bool":false}]},{"id":132,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 16-year-old boy is brought to the clinic with generalized weakness and easy bruising. His complete blood profile shows pancytopenia. Peripheral film shows giant metamyelocytes with large sausage-shaped nuclei. His bilirubin is  3 mg%. The reticulocyte count is 0.5%. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Acute leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":133,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 79-year-old woman presents to the emergency department with complaints of confusion, headache, and tinnitus. Her general practitioner has recently started her on an analgesic; the physician on duty is worried she may have taken too much. Which of the following would most likely explain her symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Paracetamol","bool":false},{"option":"Mefanamic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Codeine","bool":false},{"option":"Diclofenac sodium","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":true}]},{"id":134,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 68-year-old woman comes to the physician because of a history of easy fatigability and back pain. On examination, she is anemic and has tender bones. Her initial investigations show Hb 9.8 g/dL, MCV 84 fl, platelets 141 x 10^3/L, creatinine 2.3 mg/dL, ALP 84 IU, and SGPT 32 IU. Bone scan shows lytic lesions. Which of the following is the next best step in diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Serum protein electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"Urinary immune fixation","bool":false},{"option":"Serum immune fixation","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary protein electrophoresis","bool":false}]},{"id":135,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 25-year-old female is diagnosed with porphyria variegate. Which of the following may be included as part of the specific management of this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Courses of venesection","bool":false},{"option":"Use of beta carotene","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous glucose as provision of 55 KJ per day","bool":false},{"option":"Avoidance of agents that can precipitate the condition","bool":true},{"option":"Use of sunscreens","bool":false}]},{"id":136,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 50-year-old female who has recently been diagnosed with hypertension presents to the clinic for a routine follow-up examination. On workup, she has abnormal values of hemoglobin (Hb) 7.4 mg/dl, MCV 84 fl, creatinine 5.4 mg/dl, blood urea nitrogen (BUN) 65 mmol/L, potassium 5.2 mEq/L, sodium 130 mEq/L, phosphorus 5.0 mEq/L, calcium 6.7 mg/dl. Which of the following is the most likely cause of decreased Hb in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Drug-induced gastritis","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"B12 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of erythropoietin","bool":true},{"option":"Folic acid deficiency","bool":false}]},{"id":137,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 16-year-old boy presents to the emergency department with the complaint of swelling of the right knee joint after trivial trauma. History is significant for similar incidences over the past 4 years. Their family history is positive for a bleeding disorder. Investigations show: hemoglobin -  10 g/dL, white cell count - 5,000/uL, platelets - 200,000/uL, factor VIII - normal, prothrombin time (PT) - 16 seconds (control - 14 seconds), activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT) - 48 seconds (control - 35 seconds). Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Von willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Acquired hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":true},{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":false}]},{"id":138,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 40-year-old man presents with easy fatigability. Investigations reveal hemoglobin (Hb) - 9 g/dL, mean corpuscular volume (MCV) - 105 fL, and spherocytes on peripheral blood film. Which of the following is the most common abnormality in hereditary spherocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Protein 4.1 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Adducin deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-spectrin deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Alpha-spectrin deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Glycophorin C deficiency","bool":false}]},{"id":139,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 45-year-old male presents to you with complaints of early satiety and heaviness for the past 2 months. He also gives history of blurring of vision and severe headache for the past week. His labs show hemoglobin - 10.1 mg/dL, white blood cells - 79,000/mm3, platelets - 950,000 and left myeloid shift on peripheral smear. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Myelofibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia vera rubra","bool":false},{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Essential thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":true}]},{"id":140,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 10-year-old boy presents to you with a complaint of severe pain in his hands and feet. He is febrile, mildly jaundiced, and dehydrated. Labs show hemoglobin 0 5.6 gm/dL, reticulocyte count - 8%, total bilirubin - 2.5 mg, SGPT - 20. Family history is significant for a similar illness in his brother 1 year ago. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell trait","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute hepatitis","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell disease with vaso-occlusive crisis","bool":true}]},{"id":141,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is the most common site for extrapulmonary tuberculosis?","answers":[{"option":"Central nervous system","bool":false},{"option":"Pericardium","bool":false},{"option":"Bones and joint","bool":false},{"option":"Gastrointestinal tract","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":true}]},{"id":142,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is true regarding paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH)?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombosis is uncommon in PNH","bool":false},{"option":"Flow cytometry does not help in diagnosis","bool":false},{"option":"It does not progress to myelodysplasia or acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"It causes persistent hemoglobinuria","bool":false},{"option":"It can be suspected in confusing cases of hemolytic anemia or pancytopenia","bool":true}]},{"id":143,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 16-year-old male presents to you with complaints of fatigue, backache, leg pain, and fever. His labs show hemoglobin of 7 g/dL. Which of the following is the definitive diagnostic test for sickle cell anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Genetic screening of parents","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle solubility test","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle shaped cells on blood film","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocytosis","bool":false}]},{"id":144,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"An 18-year-old boy presents to the clinic and you observe on examination rubbery lymph nodes in the cervical and axillary region, along with a history of weight loss for the past 4 months. Which of the following is the gold standard test for establishing the diagnosis of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Lymph node biopsy","bool":true},{"option":"CT scan abdomen","bool":false},{"option":"CT scan neck","bool":false},{"option":"CT scan chest","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false}]},{"id":145,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is a poor source of folic acid?","answers":[{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Eggs","bool":true},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Bananas","bool":false},{"option":"Green leafy vegetable","bool":false}]},{"id":146,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"Which of the following is not an indication of anticoagulation therapy?","answers":[{"option":"Intracardiac thrombus","bool":false},{"option":"Internal carotid artery thrombus","bool":false},{"option":"Protein C or protein S deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Acute stroke secondary to hypertension","bool":true},{"option":"Stroke resulting from atrial fibrillation","bool":false}]},{"id":147,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2020","question":"A 65-year-old man presents to the hematology outpatient department with a 6 months history of tiredness, weight loss, and shortness of breath. On examination, there is massive splenomegaly but no lymphadenopathy. Lab investigations show hemoglobin - 9.8 g/dL, white blood cells - 240,000/mm3, and platelets - 458,000/mm3. Peripheral blood film shows increased number of neutrophils and myelocytes with prominent basophils and normocytic normochromic red blood cells. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false}]}]
export default arr